FABOWALE, JOHNSON TAIWO

[B.TECH, CFOT, CCNA, ITIL]

12. POPOOLA ESTATE, IYANA-ODO, IYANA IPAJA, LAGOS.

johnsonfabowale@gmail.com, +234(0)7032972991, 08055574475.

Gender: Male LinkedIn Link: linkedin.com/in/fabowale-johnson-taiwo Nationality: Nigerian

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

I have notable experience in Network Performance Management, Integration and Support to achieve timely project delivery. I am good at identifying areas of need and proffer necessary solutions to improve overall performance. I am teachable with firm commitment to continuous learning.

KEY ACHIEVEMENTS

- 55% growth in regional revenue in 2019 over the previous year because of various effective optimization of Network parameters carried out which improved customers' experience.
- Increased Data Consumption across the 4 states in my region by 50% through strategic capacity upgrade of 3G sites in major cities and tertiary institutions.
- Increased regional Voice Traffic by 45% through timely RF Planning and Optimization activities to relief 2G Congestion and improve Quality of Service (QoS)
- Improved overall Network Availability by 40% as a result of prompt detection and resolution of performance impacting alarms through effective collaboration with Operation and Maintenance (O & M) and Field Support teams.
- My team won "Optimization Star Performer-2019" in recognition of the team's strategic stride that resulted in improved network quality and significant growth in revenue.

KEY COMPETENCIES

- Leadership and Management.
- Project Management.
- Vendor Management.
- Communication and Negotiation.
- Network Performance Management.
- RF Planning and Optimization.
- Network/System Integration and Support.
- Strong analytical and troubleshooting skills.
- Preventive and Corrective Maintenance Skills.
- Deep understanding of Telecom Network Architecture.
- Information Technology (IT) Service Management.
- User Support.
- Good interpersonal relationship.
- Proficient in Microsoft Word, Excel, PowerPoint, BI and Outlook.

WORKING EXPERIENCE

NETWORK QUALITY ENGINEER (Performance & Optimization) at Globacom Limited

(May, 2018

– Till date)

RESPONSIBILITY

My duties include but not limited to:

- I perform overall Network Performance Management and optimization by carrying out technical activities to maintain network Accessibility, Mobility, Retainability and Availability Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) within acceptable standard thresholds
- I ensure proper management and implementation of all network changes according to the organization change management process and procedures
- I make use of various Network Performance and Optimization tools for Network Planning, Data Analysis, Capacity Upgrade and Performance Management.

- Escalation, tracking and Support of on-site engineers for various Traffic/ performance impacting alarms resolution.
- Daily monitoring of 2G, 3G and 4G KPIs.
- Monitor the Network Elements to ensure optimal network performance by analyzing the Network Statistics and KPIs which has led to the continuous increase in revenue.
- Raising necessary Work Order for integration of new 2G, 3G and 4G sites.
- Performing effective audits of company assets and making recommendations for necessary investment to improve network performance.
- Accessibility, Mobility, Retainability and Availability KPIs monitoring to ensure delivery of optimum QoS.
- Location Area Code (LAC) Optimization to improve Paging.
- GSM Cell Neighbour Audit. (2G to 2G, 2G to 3G, External Neighbour Cell Audit and Modification).
- UMTS Cell Neighbour Audit. (Intra Frequency, Inter frequency, 3G to 2G, External Neighbour Cell Audit and Modification).
- LTE Neighbor Planning and Audit.
- Handover Problems Identification, Analysis and Neighbour Optimization to improve network performance.
- Analysis and monitoring of NodeB's on Resource issues: CE, Power, Code and WBBP board utilization, TCP utilization.
- Monitoring for Inference (RTWP issues) and taking necessary action for effective resolution.
- HSPA Throughput analysis, optimization, and monitoring to improve customer experience.
- Monitoring and analysis of the network parameters such as Availability, RRC, CDR, CSSR, HO, CS-RAB, PS-RAB, HSPA RAB, TCH, SDCCH, CQI, etc.
- Transmission issues Support, Escalations (IUB packet loss) and follow up to ensure quick resolution.
- Execute RF Optimization to optimize 3G/2G clusters through regular drive test/performance data analysis, raising Work Order for necessary adjustment.
- Validation of Work Order from Planning Unit before implementation.
- Hands on experience Huawei (M2000, PRS), ZTE (NetNumen), MapInfo, Google Earth, and Network Drive Test Tools.
- Advance use of Microsoft Office tools, especially Excel, PowerPoint, and BI for Business Intelligent decisions.

FIBER OPTIC PROJECT COORDINATOR at Anchor Telecom (Huawei Staff Outsource Company) (March, 2018 – May, 2018)

RESPONSIBILITY

My duties include but not limited to:

- I ensured adequate provision and management of both human and material resources required for project actualization by strategic planning and coordination.
- I managed 14 teams of 28 field Engineers to solve our clients' (MTN and AIRTEL) toughest Fiber network challenges by ensuring 24/7 network uptime across all manage segments as well as providing quick resolution to network failure to minimize MTTR, thereby exceeding Service Level Agreement (SLA).
- To impart field engineers with relevant technical knowledge and guide them on best practices.
- Coordinated Proactive Preventive Maintenance activities across my managed segments to prevent avoidable network failure.
- Coordinated project logistics activities and ensure all necessary tools and materials are provided to field engineers and Back Office staff at the right time.
- As a Project Coordinator, I served as Single Point of Contact (SPOC) between the company and its client (Huawei Technologies, Lagos, Nigeria).
- Communicated timely with clients and management on the progress of the projects and advise both accordingly.
- Worked closely with the Project Manager to ensure successful project completion.
- Active involvement in technical and managerial meetings with project stakeholders.
- Managed project plans in accordance with the set objectives.

TEAM LEAD, FIBER NETWORK at Raeanna Nigeria Limited (August, 2016 – March, 2018)

RESPONSIBILITY

- Coordinate team activities to achieve 24/7 network uptime.
- Performed emergency Corrective maintenance (restoration) within specified MTTR to satisfy SLA.
- I handled resources management for seamless operation.
- Performed Preventive Maintenance of the Fiber Optics route.

- Provide daily/weekly reports to the management.
- Carried out monthly OTDR end-to-end test of the Fiber link to ensure optimal network performance.
- Performed Site Survey.
- Proficient in the use of Fiber Optics equipment (Splicing Machine, OTDR, Optical Laser Source,
- Optical Power Meter, VFL, e. t. c).
- Provide management with a proper financial report for effective planning.
- Understanding of Fiber terminologies, fiber cable management, and fiber link budgeting.
- Understanding and accurate interpretation of Design drawing and As-Built drawings for Fiber networks.

FIBER PROJECT ENGINEER at Teletok Nigeria Limited

(July, 2015 - May, 2016)

RESPONSIBILITY

- Supervised Globacom FOC projects implementation.
- Responsible for fiber splicing and Fiber testing.
- Supervised fiber cable route trenching, blowing/pulling and backfilling activities.
- Prepared project status weekly report for the management.
- Engaged in technical discussion and resolution of problems with vendors and subcontractors.
- Performed optical Fiber link maintenance.
- Successfully handled other responsibilities in the related field: Route Surveying, Fiber Optic Cable preparation, Splice Closures preparation, Optical Loss Test, troubleshooting and documentation, Fiber Optic splicing (Fusion), etc.

PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATION

Cisco Certified Network Associate (CCNA)

Cisco ID: CSCO13261794.

Information Technology Infrastructure Library (ITIL)

Certificate Number: 04159218-01-DQBY.

Certified Fiber Optic Technician (CFOT)

Fiber Optic Association License: 7180273.

Certificate of National Service.

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATIONS WITH DATE

Ladoke Akintola University of Technology, Ogbomoso

2009 - 2015.

Bachelor of Technology (B.TECH) in Electronic and Electrical Engineering.

Graduated with Cumulative Grade Point Average of 4.11 out of 5.0 (Second Class Upper)

Graduated as one of the top 10% in a very competitive class.

Keen interest in Communication and Electrical Instrumentation.

Constructed a DC Refrigerator as a final year project with distinctions.